Okay, so in this video then,
we are going to just basically
talk about addressing some
impediments, obstacles and blockers.
Now these three terms,
impediment, obstacle
and blockers, they're
generally synonymous.
They usually, I mean, they basically mean
the same thing, they're generally
synonymous, and PMI will
actually, most of the time,
you know, generally just
use them synonymously.
However, there are one or two little
subtle differences.
There's very, very subtle differences,
right, that I just want to explain,
just want to mention.
An impediment generally is something,
some action that slows down progress,
right, hinders progress,
whereas an obstacle and
a blocker is actually
going to stop the work.
That's going to stop the progress
altogether.
Obstacles and blockers, right, they
call stoppages, whereas an impediment.
slows down the progress, it just hinders
the progress.
So that's the basic difference between an
impediment and then
an obstacle and a blocker.
Now, difference in an obstacle and a
blocker, just at a very, very high level.
And again, generally these terms are used
interchangeably.
But, you know, there are these little
subtle differences.
So an obstacle will be something that
prevents the work from starting in the
first place, whereas the blocker will be
stopping the work altogether.
So as a simple example, then, an
impediment here.
So an impediment, remember, it slows down,
hinders the progress.
For example, a team not coming to a quick
decision.
That's going to slow the slow down
decision making.
That's going to slow down.
The entire team can't come to a quick
decision.
I mean, they're going
to come to a decision
eventually, but that's
to slow down progress.
Obstacle on the other hand, right?
It basically it prevents a work from being
started, for example, in the first place,
right?
So, for example, we can't get a permit.
So we work cannot start until we get a
permit.
So that's prevented the work from even
starting.
Whereas a blocker is something that is
going to cause a stoppage.
A work's already started, but now the work
suddenly stopped.
That would be a blocker, right?
So, for example, you know, you're using a
vendor's product and an example here where
companies stop seasons vendors product,
right?
So we've been told we don't have a
relationship with this vendor anymore.
So all of a sudden we cannot use that
product.
Right.
So now we're, you know, we're halfway
through this project.
Now we suddenly have to stop.
So like I said, these terms are generally
synonymous, right?
But these are just a couple of subtle
differences between the three of them.
So an impediment slows down.
Think of an obstacle as some kind of
barrier that prevents, say, the work from
being started, and then a blocker is,
it's going to stop the work.
Now, we need to address them.
We need to address these impediments,
obstacles and blockers.
We need to identify them at first.
And then we need to deal with them.
Right.
So, where are we identifying them?
So in an agile environment, a backlog
item.
So as we are assessing the backlogs,
as we are creating the backlog.
So remember the product
owner is the one that is responsible
for prioritizing user stories
to create the backlog item.
Right.
Well, they may be identifying some
impediments and obstacles there.
So we can't start this user story until
another user story is complete.
So we've gathered these user stories,
but we can't actually start this.
There's a whole bunch of other user
stories that we need to get.
So now that can identify, you know,
so basically now we need to reach out to
stay called us to get some
more user stories, that can
identify an impediment or a
blocker and that kind of thing.
Or let's say we realize that we've got
this user story, but it's too big.
It's more of an epic, it's more or more of
a feature than a user story.
So we realize that now, so now we need to
break it down.
This is a simple example, just assessing.
So just assessing these backlog items,
that could potentially identify any
impediments or blockers and so and so
forth.
Daily stand-up meeting, right?
Well, that's one of the reasons of having
a daily stand-up meeting.
Remember, in a daily stand-up, each
team member is addressing three questions.
What did I accomplish yesterday?
What am I going to work on today?
And what impediments are there?
What obstacles, blockers?
What issues are there?
So you'll be identifying these impediments
during the daily stand-up meeting.
And those issues,
those obstacles, blockers,
impediments are basically
taken offline, right?
And the team facilitator is the one that
is responsible then for addressing them,
removing them, removing those obstacles,
removing those impediments.
Now, they might need to bring
other team members together
in order to do that, but
again, that's taken offline.
It's not discussed in the daily stand-up.
Because remember the daily stand-up is
only 10-15-minute meeting, right?
has to be specifically time boxed to 10 or
15 minutes.
Also, let's think about this.
A potential impediment obstacle or blocker
is a risk.
If it's a potential, then it's a risk.
So as we're identifying risk,
as you're reviewing our risks,
we could potentially identify
an impediment or a blocker.
So a risk by itself might be an
impediment.
right, it might potentially slow down
progress or it might, you know, stop.
So, you know, if I identified the risk
that a vendor may delay shipment of raw
materials, well, that might completely
prevent us from the start, you know,
start in one of our activities.
Or let's say we've started
this activity, the next
stage of this activity is to
use these raw materials.
Vendid delay shipment of raw materials,
now that's slowed us down.
or that's completely put
this activity at a standstill
until we get the, until
we get the raw materials.
So now we don't know if that's going to
happen.
We just identified it could happen.
That's a risk.
Now, if it's already happened,
right, an impediment obstacle or blocker
by, you know, by default, if it's
happened, then it's an issue at that point.
Right.
So where would we document that in the
issue log?
Or we could document it in the issue log.
We also need to track the impediment.
or blocker, so you may create what's known
as an impediment task board.
So this is another document
that PMI mentioned,
something called an impediment task board.
And it basically could be used to show,
you know, impediments that have been
addressed, right, which we haven't,
what we started working on.
So similar to a task board or similar to a
Kanban board that we talked about in a,
in a separate video, may have an
impediment task board.
I don't know there may be some of the
software applications that you could be
using as well to track impediments
obstacles blockers and so and so far okay
so those are the basic difference then
between the three three items as I said
most of the time they're going to be used
synonymously but these are just a couple
of the subtle differences between an
impediment an obstacle and a blocker